all right so I'm sitting here with with
dr. Jordan Peterson we were gonna talk
about the weird overlap between our
books there's a sort of metafiction
aspect of it because Jordan had written
the rules for I was a Korra entry
yeah it's 32 rules in Cora that's right
42 rules got pared down so there's gonna
be like 19 sequels right that's right
rolling him out and and I thought they
were amazing and so I was writing orphan
acts I was writing the first book in the
series and in orphan Acts my main
character is an assassin and he has
these sort of 10 commandments that are
the operational rules for an assassin
and I wanted something to offset that
for a kid who's in his life who lives
downstairs from him who's being raised
as a good human instead of as an
assassin and I wanted to set a rules
that would kind of counterbalance that
and at the time I was reading Jordan's
rules that he listed and so I sort of
used those as a counterbalance as sort
of positive masculinity to use to use
this horrible phrase that the
well-trodden term but to actually show
how somebody might be raised properly
instead of as an international assassin
and at the time you know you were a mere
professor at utoronto I thought what
could possibly be controversial about
this yeah right and so so that's how it
sort of started yeah well it was fun to
see you know when you create something
like those rules I wrote them for Cora
and I'd written like 50 Cora answers and
some of them got disproportionately
popular which is exactly what you'd
expect because some things get
disproportionately popular and and that
Cora rules attracted a lot of attention
by Korres standards or by the standards
of what I was reading on Cora and then
you would pit you pick them up and I
thought it's one of the things that's
very interesting about doing something
creatively is that you sort of launch it
like you launch a note in a bottle on
the ocean and you have no idea where
it's going to end up and so that was the
first interesting manifestation of those
rules outside of the Cora
container so to speak and then of course
part of our discussion about the rules
also led to their encapsulation and 12
rules for life and that was much later
and it's been interesting to see how
that overlap has developed as well well
it's also weird to see what
connects like it's so funny with with
orphan acts when I was first adapting
and the big thing with that is that my
character kind of interacts he's an
archetypal character like a Jack Reacher
Jason Bourne but lives in the real world
with you and me you know so it's like
he's not you never see James Bond go
home you know just what an archetypal
character should do right it should
exist in abstraction and also be
embedded in the real world yeah but
usually you have like the High Plains
Drifter who's like off feeding his horse
and like moving on to the next town yes
I thought it'd be so fun to have them
like interacting with the annoying
Jewish woman who lives upstairs and
having an awkward confrontation with the
woman who lives downstairs who his
chemistry with so it's an archetypal
character wrestled into the real world
that's what the spider-men people did
really well the Marvel with Daniel and
spider-man they said extraordinarily
well where he has to like Reese stitches
cost you had no one thought about that
you know and he's like late for school
and all those problems exactly exactly
so that was that was sort of the motif
well that is also the problem of it's a
more complex psychological problem of of
integrating the archetypal with the real
world because there's an element of
everyone's psyche that's that's
transpersonal that's archetypal right
because to some degree you should
manifest the mythological hero in your
life but the the critical issue there is
in your life right because your life is
like your life is like the bottle that
or the lamp that the genie is in it's
like the genie is God for all intents
and purposes but it's in this little
tiny container it's like well that's
what you're like is you have this
archetypal element to your personality
which is your capacity for heroic
endeavor but it's all constrained by the
hypothetical or the trivialities of your
life and you have to you have to mediate
between those well and that's the weird
thing like you were saying one of the
things when you write is you don't
always know what's gonna connect right
you never knew that those rules would
become you know number one best-selling
book everywhere in the world
what was so interesting is there's this
one scene at the opening of orphan Acts
where he's in the elevator and he's got
a cut on his arm we don't know what it's
from and he has to fake to kind of pass
as a real person among all the people
and he's kind of covering it up but he's
got suppressors and he used the sock as
a tourniquet so he's missing a sock and
he's kind of trying to pass his secret
identity among other people
that seemed connected unbelievably with
readers with and it would it would be
like the last scene that I would have
thought and when I did the book
initially for Bradley Cooper as a
feature and I remember I was like well
if I have Bradley Cooper let me open
with some big action you show off you
thing and both his production company
and the head of the studio were like we
need the elevator saying like this
elevator scene became the iconic thing
of course because it does what you're
talk to should be some music playing in
the back like there is something yeah if
you get caught between the beard in New
York City right right but it's weird cuz
I never would have thought that would be
the thing mm-hmm
so the stuff that you send out I have
any idea why that was so attractive to
people well I think it's exactly the
thing that we were talking about is like
you don't see James Bond in that
circumstance it's so it's like this
archetypal guy has a mission is a knife
cut that he tourniquets his arm with and
then he's in the elevator that you and I
have been in and everyone's nagging him
that he's you know missed the HOA
meeting the homeowners association
meeting where they're voting on like the
new carpeting in the lobby and he's just
trying to get out of it and he's
covering so there's this wish
fulfillment fantasy aspect to it but
it's almost like our own lives and like
everyone knows what it's like to be
dealing with annoyances and logistics
but then he gets to go back to his life
is like a super secret assassin who
helps the helpless well and there's
another element of it too I would say
which is that that that that scene and
and that that context also suggests that
one of the ways that you one of the
things that you have to do in order to
put up with those mundane daily elements
of life is also to have your adventure
along with you yeah yeah so and I mean
one of the things that I've been talking
to my audience is about continually is
that you need to have a meaning in your
life that's of sufficient grandeur let's
say or sufficient power so that the
petty sufferings of life now become not
only justifiable but acceptable in the
broader context and so and sufficient
risk and sufficient risk because all
that in that and that's what puts the
adventure into it right it's like in the
elevator scene it's it's not only that
everyone can relate to the mundane it's
also that everyone can see that what
trans
the mundane is also fundamentally
necessary before otherwise you are
nothing but a collection of trivialities
and and life has so much suffering that
if you're just a collection of
trivialities you're not going to be able
to bear it so you need your heroic
adventure which is what's animating you
literally anima is the soul right that's
what Adam Amin's so that's literally
animating you well you have to put up
with being trapped in this little tiny
conveyor right I thought about this lot
when I was writing Batman I wrote Batman
for tutors for DC and I was fascinated
by this sort of seesaw tilt between
perfection and intimacy which is so
Batman you know he doesn't have a magic
ring he can't fly he just represents the
pinnacle of human discipline and
achievement it's cuz his parents died
when he was young right he's alone in
Wayne Manor there's Robin always dies
there's always a Robin and he dies he's
a playboy he doesn't have anyone
intimate and if there's no one in your
life you can maintain perfection but the
more you inch into intimacy a dog a
spouse a partner children the more that
you get this sort of conflict and
complication that starts to take over
and detract from that version of
perfection so it's like you can be
perfect without intimacy but then you're
not perfect because you have no intimacy
and so the more that you integrated it's
almost like the more that you're
accepting the realities of life but also
I think it's also one of the things it's
interesting in the Batman reference
because one of the things you see in the
Batman Joker dynamic especially the one
with Heath Ledger was the Joker was
always pushing at Batman because of the
evil of his perfections like you're this
far away from me and that
perfectionistic drive there's something
totalitarian and single-minded about it
right and then it's the encapsulation of
that in intimacy that that humanizes it
and perhaps it's sane right and so so
that uni-dimensional perfection can go
very very badly when it goes and to be
contextually constrained like that is
actually like a definition of sanity
it's something that Jung talked about
when he was commenting on Nietzsche and
and people like Nietzsche said he
believed that Nietzsche would have been
able to maintain his sanity for much
longer
assuming no physiological degeneration
had he been able to incorporate himself
within a profession and a family who
nailed him to the earth right and in a
healthy way stilts down that's right
exactly
right so I thought we'd just talk
briefly about the editing process for 12
rolls it was a lot of fun because I got
to read it all early which was yeah this
was fun so I had it featured in the
orphan X books like two years before it
came out right which is why I always
like to remind you that I'm mostly
responsible for yours yes well I do
appreciate that well I sent all the
chapters to Greg I had an editor at
penguin Craig Pyatt who was very very
helpful so I had two editors really and
other people commenting on it but I sent
each chapter to Greg and he would just
shred them he's really really good at
that and and well and very comical and
so he just be absolutely brutal with his
criticisms but it was also a also always
extremely funny it was a fast yeah well
and then I was also absolutely staggered
by how rapidly you could do that and to
point to what was working and to tell me
what wasn't working and that was
exceptionally helpful and you're very
very skilled at that so so there's the
compliment you're gonna get for me now
it was very others look now the insult
first you leave you soften me up with a
compliment and now you know but I think
what was helpful is so I mean I took
three courses from you as an
undergraduate so it's like we've been
swimming in the same waters for a long
time so it was really interesting for me
to see you know through the process you
know I have it I have a sense that goes
kind of all the way down of the ideas
room with going back to before maps of
meaning going back to the source book
articles and stuff you lectured amount
so it was really fun to see them take
hold and move from the abstract into the
ever more accessible and specific yeah
well it was useful too because you're
you've developed this intense skill in
in producing commercial widely publicly
accessible fiction and and you have a
sense of what works in terms of
narrative flow and that was very useful
to have that perspective on the way the
stories were laid out in in each of the
rules to make them to give them that
narrative punch which is necessary to
add an additional dimension of what
would you say quality to the writing I'm
glad but it's good working with someone
with like your learning curve was like
this so he's like the first one that we
went through you know if there was
something that the speed with which you
can sort of implement an assembly new
and
nation and and reflect that in writing
is unbelievable yeah well that's fun
there's a benefit of being sort of
experienced in multiple dominant Arcas I
think because there's so many things
that you've done it's such a high level
that when you add a new one the learning
curve is like this so it's also really
fun cuz it's like you know if well we'll
have a chance to do it again yeah
alright I would expect when I write the
next book or maybe an extension of 12
rules for life I presume so it's fun
bumping into you here cuz we're just
bumped into each other at this studio
today blue yeah actually halfway around
the world in one studio part but so
that's great so you work on the next one
and they'll work on the next orphan
accent good go from there
alright good to see you man